Meaning that if we accept the axiom of
infinity, which essentially just states that omega exists,
then by the power set axiom,
the power set of omega exists and is larger than omega.
But then we can take the power set of the
power set of omega, resulting in a new larger infinity.
And we can repeat this as many times as we like.
So, returning the Universe of sets which we had,
let's simplify by representing the ordinals using numbers.
Recall that each level of the hierarchy is obtained by taking the
power set of the previous level. We may define the omega'th level
of the hierarchy, as the union of each of the previous levels.
Here the union is like a limit in calculus, and this structure
V_omega, is the limit of the V_n's as n approaches infinity.
But now that we are equipped with the axiom of infinity, we
may continue by taking the power set of V_omega, to obtain V_omega+1
This means that we are now performing so-called transfinite
recursion. Again, many mathematicians, namely those with constructivist intuitions
about mathematics, don't believe in such constructions, but let's
just see how far this idea can go, because
it does lead to interesting places.
Since V omega has omega many elements, V omega +1 has 2^omega many
elements. So this slice of the hierarchy has continuum many sets in it.
Now if we look at the ordinal at this level, which is just omega+1,
it is just the set of all natural numbers with omega at the top.
So, unlike omega itself, omega plus 1 has a largest element, namely omega
Now have to quickly mention the difference between cardinals and ordinals. When
I have been saying size so far, I have been referring to
the cardinality, which is the answer to how many elements.
The ordinal numbers is the answer to how many and in what
order. This is another key difference between finite and infinite sets.
If we want to determine how many elements a
finite set has, we can simply count them.
We note that this imposes some arbitrary order of the elements,
but that this order does not affect the final result.
For infinite sets, the order we count does
in some sense affect the final result.
For example, we could consider counting the natural numbers where we first count
all of the even numbers, and then all of the odd numbers.
This would result in something which we can represent as
follows. This structure has a different order type than the
set of natural numbers in its normal ordering.
Of course the number of total elements used is the
same, but the order in which they appear is different.
Using this idea we can start to count past infinity.
So again, we start with omega, which is just another
way of saying the natural numbers in their usual ordering.
Then we can define the successor of omega, omega+1 using the
same Russian doll successor function as before. Now when we go
past infinity, we start to use Greek letters to represent ordinals
instead of regular letters, but its still the same stuff. So
omega+1 represents the ordering of omega with a single greatest element.
Then we can define omega plus 2, in the same way, and we
see that it represents the order type of omega with two greatest elements.
and then we can repeat this omega many
times, to obtain omega+omega, like we saw earlier.
We can continue using this successor function, passing through
omega times omega or omega squared, which is similar
to the rational numbers with a left endpoint.
Eventually through omega to the omega, and to even larger
ordinals such as epsilon naught, which is the fixed point
of the operation sending omega to the omega.
Meaning that epsilon naught is the least solution to
the equation epsilon equals omega to the epsilon.
But each of these ordinals are countable, meaning that they
can be put into 1 to 1 correspondence with omega.
So, we see these as different ways of re-ordering omega.
But now we can consider the set of all possible orderings
of omega, i.e. the set of all countable ordinals. If this
set is a countable ordinal, then it would be a member
of itself. But this contradicts the axiom of Foundation.
So, the set of all countable ordinals is uncountable. Meaning that there
are more ways or re-ordering omega, then there are elements in omega.
We will call this set, as Cantor did, omega 1.
Now we can repeat the same process with omega_1. So, we can
recursively apply the same successor function passing through all possible orderings of
this new larger base set omega_1. Then we can think of omega_2
as the set containing each of the orderings of omega_1, and we
know that this set has large cardinality than omega_1
So, if we just care about the cardinality, meanings how
many elements there are, we see that all of these
sets have the same size, since they are just different
orderrings of omega. We will call this size aleph_0.
And similarly these sets have the same size, whcih
we call aleph_1. And these guys have size aleph_2
Now the ordinals, such as omega, omega 1, and omega 2,
where a jump in size happens will be called cardinals.
We will now see how far this hierarchy of cardinals
can go, but first let us address a natural question.